NYSUT Memorabilia 6174 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Memorabilia
1980-1998
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174 MB
2.28 cubic feet
2.3 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
7164051
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 05, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 24, 2016
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Scope and Contents
Items from conventions and other events dating as far back as 1845 but mostly concentrating on the 1980s and 90s; includes plaques, campaign pins, buttons, name tags, T-shirts, tote bags, and other items.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/017 MB 6174: NYSUT Records 6174 AV: NYSUT Audio-Visual Materials 6174 OH: NYSUT Oral History Interviews 6174 P: NYSUT Photographs 6174 PUBS: NYSUT Publications 6174/001: NYSUT President's Office Files 6174/001 P: NYSUT President's Office Photographs 6174/002: NYSUT Vice President's Office files 6174/003: NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services. Files 6174/004: NYSUT Field Services Department Files 6174/004 AV: NYSUT Field Services Department Audio-Visual Material 6174/005: NYSUT Legislative Department Files 6174/006: NYSUT Public Relations Department Files 6174/007: NYSUT New York Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education Files 6174/008: NYSUT Federation of Nurses and Health Professionals Files 6174/009: NYSUT Teacher Education Conference Board Files 6174/010: NYSUT Convention files 6174/011: NYSUT Mid-Hudson Regional Office Files 6174/012: NYSUT "Teachers United: The Rise of NYSUT" Research Notes 6174/013 AV: NYSUT Representative Assembly (RA) Audio-Visual materials 6174/014: NYSUT Alan Lubin Files 6174/015: NYSUT Boards of Directors Meetings 6174/016: NYSUT Vice-President's Office Maria Neira. Files 6174/017: NYSUT General Officers Records 6174/017 AV: NYSUT General Officers Audio-Visual Materials 6174/017 P: NYSUT General Officers Photographs 6174/018: NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, Maria Neira Files 6174/019: NYSUT Biography File
Teachers' union--New York (State); New York State United Teachers
7164051
- New York State Martin Luther King, Jr. Institute and Commission Plaque (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  In Recognition for Service and Leadership, Thomas Y. Hobart, President, NYSUT-- 5x7 etched glass plaque with wooden stand
- AFT paddles (Box 1, Folder 2)
  3 paper paddles shaped like apples
- Cotton and paper signs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  cotton-- "Aylwin, Presidente de Todos Los Chilenos"; paper -- Bodegas y Vinedos Giol, Maipu, Mendoza, Buenos Aires
- Alfred E. Smith Award: For conspicuous Service in Behalf of Public Education to (Box 1, Folder 4)
  5x7 wood plaque
- AFT hats (Box 1, Folder 5)
  1 cotton hat - "American Federation of Teachers"; 2 foam visors - "American Federation of Teachers"
- Union Leadership Institute, American Federation of Teachers - badges (Box 1, Folder 6)
  name tags - American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO, Staff; Union leadership Institute, Charles Santelli, Director of Research and Educational Services NYSUT
- Stickers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  AFT Clinton/Gore bumper stickers; Solidarity Day '91, august 31, Washington, D.C. be there! American Federation of Labor & Congress of Industrial Organizations; Be there! Solidarity Day '91, ALF-CIO, August 31, Washington D.C. - roll of stickers
- New York State Council of Educational Association Plaque (Box 1, Folder 8)
  "The New York State Council of Educational Associations expresses its appreciation to The New York State United Teachers for their generous support and service in the production of their monograph on Multiculturalism, April 1994" - 8x10 plaque
- Buttons (13) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  AFT; AFT; aft Clinton/Gore; 1888 One Hundred 1988 Years of Solidarity, Rochester & Vicinity Labor Council AFL-CIO; It's Time for them to GO! Vote Democratic (2); Stop Tuition Tax Credits; I was there! Solidarity Day '91, AFL-CIO, August 31, Washington, D.C.; Right to Strike, Right to Organize, Solidarity Day, August 31, 1991, Washington, D.C.
- Buttons and Pen (Box 1, Folder 10)
  5 of same button - The Real Education Candidate Clinton, NYSUT; 1 Pen - Civitas
- Buttons, Tie Tacks, Name Plates (Box 1, Folder 11)
  3 buttons - Bill Clinton For President; 2 push pins - Clinton/Gore; 1 pin - National Rainbow Coalition; 1 push pin - Civitas; 1 tie tack with a torch on it; 1 pin - Solidarity Day '91, AFL CIO, August 31, Washington, D.C.; 2 name plates - James M. Balassone, 1963-1964 and Helen P. Maney, 1959-1960; 1 push pin - CBY; 1 push pin - NYSUT, 1972-1982 (was removed from 6174/010, box 1, FF2)
- NYSUT name tag (Box 1, Folder 12)
  NYSUT, United Teachers, AFT, New York State United Teachers (Paul Cole)
- Buttons (Box 1, Folder 13)
  1 - I Toed the Line, Chicago Teachers Union, 73; 1 - Free to be You and Me; 1 - Try a Virgin Island, St. Croix, St. John, St. Thomas
- Assorted Name Tags and Business Cards (Box 1, Folder 14)
  luggage tag - Chicago, PSEA, Pennsylvania State Education Association; pin - Teacher Unity, NEA, AFT, Merge; NYSUT Business Cards for James Conti; name tags - Attorneys for Teacher Law Seminar, American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO; 1980 Representative Assembly, New York State United Teachers; AFT, American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO; New York State, Public Employees Federation, AFL-CIO, Guest; NYSUT, United Teachers, New Presidents Workshop
- Buttons - (13); Name Plates (2) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  The Hunter's Horn, Irish Power; Unity Independence; Our Position, No Tuition, Legislative Conference, Boycott - Non-UFW Grapes; Non-Violence is our strength; P.O.W.'s, Never Have a Nice Day; MIA, Missing or Prisoner; I Do Not Want To Strike. But I Will; (Apple with an X thru it); Teachers, AFT, United!; State Employees for PEF, N.Y.S. Public Employees Federation; NYSTA UTNY Teacher Unity --- name plates -- NYSTA, New York State Teachers Association, James Conti; New York State Teachers Association, National Education Association
- Buttons, Push Pins (Box 1, Folder 16)
  12 push pins shaped like a foot; 3 push pins - NYSUT United Teachers; 1 push pin shaped like NY, New York State United Teachers; 1 pin - PSA; 1 - Boycott non-union Lettuce; 1 - Rossomando, Executive Committee; 1 - McGovern
- Medallion (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Gold circular medallion - New York State Teachers Association, 1845
- Loose in box items (Box 1, Folder 18)
  t-shirt - AFT Merger, R.I.P.; t-shirt - Solidarity Day '91; T-shirt - Vote, November 3, Good for Education, Bill Clinton; cap - Union Yes, NYSUT
- small cloth bag, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  NYSUT, 15th Annual Representative Assembly, April 2-4, 1987, Albany, New York
- NYSUT: A Union of Professionals (fold up -- re-usable bag) (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Push Pins (2) -- AFT, Past President and AFT-Code (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Western Union Telegram -- from Senator John F Kennedy (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Regret very much but due to busy schedule it will be impossible for me to accept your very kind invitation for me to speak at your central zone meeting on October 16th at Syracuse. Extremely sorry. Many thanks for thinking of me
- Amendment to Charter, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  The University of the State of New York, Education Dept. -- The Trustees of the Teachers Homegranted February 28, 1980
- Tie (framed), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Tie with clock design -- note: March 24, 1997 -- Dear Edie: Al had made scores of memorable speeches. His speech in 1976, subsequently entitled Keep the Clock, was one which had an enormous effect in helping to keep NYSUT united
- NYSUT-Sign for Solidarity Day '91 (Box 3)
  - Sign (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Large sign - NYSUT - Solidarity Day '91
- NYSUT badges, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  2 - Representative Assembly, NYSUT, 25th Anniversary, Delegate badges (one with a ribbon, one without) --- pulled from 6174/010, box 3/ff22, caption RA Delegate Kit, 1998
- NYSUT push pin (Box 4, Folder 2)
  NYSUT 300,000 -- removed from 6174/010 -- box 3/ff7 - caption RA Delegate Kit, march 22-25
- Push pins (2) and Pen, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  1- shaped like a yellow ribbon, tied in a bow; 1- NYSUT; 1 Pen from Mutual of Omaha - items removed from 6174/010 - box 3/ff9 - caption -- RA Delegate Kit - 1991
- NYSUT Cloth tote bag (Box 4, Folder 4)
  10th Anniversary, 1972-1982 -- NYSUT United Teachers